Preliminary guide to the Caird Engineering Works records 1895-1985
Montana Historical Society Research Center
Caird Engineering Works records
1895-1985
Montana Historical Society Archives
No collection number; partially processed
Caird Engineering Works
80 linear feet
Caird Engineering Works was a metal works firm in Helena, Montana. This collection (1895-1985) consists primarily of pattern and order records (1896-1985). The orders, which include itemized order sheets and in many cases engineering drawings, are in numerical order. Access is provided by the customer order ledgers and by the job/pattern/price books. In addition, there are correspondence, financial records, subject files, and miscellany including orders and pattern sketches.
This collection is arranged into five series: 1) Pattern Records, 2) General Correspondence, 3) Employment Records, 4) Financial Records, and 5) Miscellany.
Collection is open for research. Please note this collection is only partially processed.
Acquisition information available upon request
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Caird Engineering Works
Foundries--Montana--History.
Helena (Mont.)--Commerce.
Montana
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Pattern Records
  - Customer order ledger (these ledgers serve as a customer index to the order books), 1896-1900 (Volume 1)
  - Customer order ledger, 1900-1902 (Volume 2)
  - Customer order ledgers, A-D, E-L, M, N-Z, 1903-1953 (Volume 3-6)
  - Customer order ledger, circa 1933-1936 (Volume 7)
  - Customer order ledger, circa 1945-1960 (Volume 8)
  - Customer order ledger, circa 1947-1960 (Volume 9)
  - Order books (16) #1-4877, 1895-1903 (Box 1-2)
  - Sketch sheet index, 1927 (Box 2a)
  - Orders #1-4400 [scattered: include itemized order and in many cases engineering drawings], 1896-1900 (Box 3-3a)
  - Orders #4401-67,154 [include itemized order and in many cases engineering drawings], 1896-1900 (Box 4-42)
  - Job book [organized by type of piece] [the job book and pattern book serve as a subject index to order books], circa 1900-1930 (Volume 10)
  - Pattern book [organized by type of piece], circa 1896-1930 (Volume 11)
  - Price book [organized by type of piece], circa 1910s-1920s (Volume 11a)
- General Correspondence
  - Alphabetically arranged correspondence and subject files, circa 1970-1985 (Box 43-45)
- Employment Records
  - Employee earning record, circa 1941-1960 (Volume 12)
  - Payroll, 1942, 1950-1971 (Volume 13-15)
  - Payroll, 1942, 1950-1971 (Box 46)
  - Payroll: office, 1950-1959 (Volume 16)
- Financial Records
  - Cash book/journals, 1903-1926 (Box 47)
  - Cash books, 1941-1960 (Volume 17-18)
  - Check distribution registers, 1941-1980 (Volume 19-22)
  - General journals, 1924-1934, 1941-1980 (Volume 23-25)
  - General journals, 1903-1970 (Box 48-49)
  - Purchase journals/invoice registers, 1941-1980 (Volume 27-28)
  - Purchase journals/invoice registers, 1941-1980 (Box 50)
  - Purchase ledger [supplies bought from others], circa 1940-1960 (Volume 29)
  - Recapitulation of invoices [purchase journals?], 1903-1941 (Volume 30-31)
  - Sales journals, 1941-1960 (Volume 32-35)
  - Sales journals, 1941-1960 (Box 51)
  - Taxes, 1978-1986 (Box 52-53)
  - Miscellaneous (includes insurance record, inventories, machine shop time cards, notes payable), 1912-1940 (Box 54)
- Miscellany
  - Miscellaneous (includes union contracts, stockholder ledger, files on customers and suppliers, etc.), circa 1960s-1980s (Box 55-57)